So, about three years ago I was in London,
إذاً منذ حوالي ثلاث سنوات كنت في لندن
and somebody called Howard Burton came to me and said,
أتى إليّ شخص يُدعى هوارد بورتون و قال لي
I represent a group of people,
أنا أُمثل مجموعة من الأشخاص
and we want to start an institute in theoretical physics.
ونريد أن نُؤسس معهداً في الفيزياء النظرية
We have about 120 million dollars, and we want to do it well.
لدينا ما يقارب 120 مليون دولار، ونريد أن نؤسسه بشكل جيد
We want to be in the forefront fields,
نريد أن نكون في الطليعة
and we want to do it differently.
ونريد أن نؤسسه بشكل مختلف
We want to get out of this thing
نريد أن نخرج من أن
where the young people have all the ideas, and the old people have all the power
الشباب يمتلكون كل الأفكار، والأشخاص المتقدمين بالعمر يمتلكون كل النفوذ
and decide what science gets done.
لنقرر ما هي العلوم التي يجب أن تُنجز.
It took me about 25 seconds to decide that that was a good idea.
لقد استغرقت مني مدة 25 ثانية لأقرر أن هذه فكرة جيدة.
Three years later, we have the Perimeter Institute for Theoretical Physics
بعد 3 سنوات، أصبح لدينا معهد بيرميتر للفيزياء النظرية
in Waterloo, Ontario. It’s the most exciting job I’ve ever had.
في ووترلو في أونتاريو، كان هذا إلى حد كبير أكثر عمل مثير قُمت به.
And it’s the first time I’ve had a job where I’m afraid to go away
وكانت هذه المرة الأولى التي كان لدي عمل أخشى أن أتركه.
because of everything that’s going to happen in this week when I’m here.
و ذلك بسبب كل الأشياء التي ستحدث هذا الأسبوع و أنا هنا
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
But in any case, what I’m going to do in my little bit of time
على أي حال، ما سأخبركم به في وقتي القليل،
is take you on a quick tour of some of the things
سيأخذكم بجولة سريعة عن بعض الأشياء
that we talk about and we think about.
التي نتحدث عنها ونفكر بها.
So, we think a lot about what really makes science work?
نحن نفكر كثيراً ما هي حقاً آلية عمل العلم؟
The first thing that anybody who knows science,
أول شيء يفكر به أي شخص يدرك العلم،
and has been around science,
أو لديه خبرة في العلم.
is that the stuff you learn in school as a scientific method
هو أن الأشياء التي تعلمتها في المدرسة وفقاً للمنهج العلمي
is wrong. There is no method.
هي خاطئة، لا توجد طريقة علمية.
On the other hand, somehow we manage to reason together
من ناحية أخرى، نحن نخطط بطريقة ما لنفكر سوياً
as a community, from incomplete evidence
كمجتمع، من براهين ناقصة،
to conclusions that we all agree about.
إلى استنتاجات نتفق عليها جميعاً.
And this is, by the way, something that a democratic society also has to do.
وهذا بالمناسبة ما يتوجب على المجتمع الديمقراطي القيام به.
So how does it work?
إذاً، ما هي آلية العمل؟
Well, my belief is that it works
حسناً، اعتقادي بأن العمل يسير
because scientists are a community bound together by an ethics.
لأن العلماء هم عبارة عن مجتمع مُلزم بالأخلاق.
And here are some of the ethical principles.
و هنا بعض المبادئ الأخلاقية.
I’m not going to read them all to you because I’m not in teacher mode.
و لكنني لن أقوم بقراءتها عليكم، لأني لست بموضع المعلم
I’m in entertain, amaze mode.
أنا ضيف، متعجب.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
But one of the principles is that everybody
و لكن واحدة من المبادئ، هي أن الجميع
who is part of the community gets to fight and argue
الذين هم جزء من المجتمع يحاربون ويجادلون
as hard as they can for what they believe.
بكل قوتهم عن الذي يؤمنون به.
But we’re all disciplined by the understanding
و لكن كلنا منضبطين بفهم
that the only people who are going to decide, you know,
أن وحدهم الأشخاص الذين سوف يقررون، كما تعلمون،
whether I’m right or somebody else is right,
سواء كنت أنا الصحيح أو غيري
are the people in our community in the next generation,
هم الأشخاص في مجتمعنا في الجيل القادم
in 30 and 50 years.
بعد 30 أو 50 سنة.
So it’s this combination of respect
لذا هذا المزيج من احترام
for the tradition and community we’re in,
التقاليد و المجتمع الذي نعيش به
and rebellion that the community requires to get anywhere,
والتمرد الذي يتطلبه المجتمع للوصول إلى أي مكان
that makes science work.
هذا الذي يجعل العلم يعمل.
And being in this process of being in a community
و كوننا في عملية كوننا في مجتمع
that reasons from shared evidence to conclusions,
يُفكر من البراهين المشتركة للوصول إلى الاستنتاجات
I believe, teaches us about democracy.
أعتقد أن هذا يعلمنا الديمقراطية.
Not only is there a relationship between the ethics of science
لا توجد فقط علاقة بين أخلاقيات العلم
and the ethics of being a citizen in democracy,
وأخلاقيات كوننا مواطنين في مجتمع ديمقراطي
but there has been, historically, a relationship
بل كان هناك تاريخياً علاقة
between how people think about space and time, and what the cosmos is,
بين كيف يفكر الناس عن الزمان و المكان و ما هو الكون
and how people think about the society that they live in.
و كيف يفكر الناس عن المجتمع الذين يعيشون فيه
And I want to talk about three stages in that evolution.
و أريد التحدث عن ثلاث مراحل من هذا التحول
The first science of cosmology that was anything like science
العلم الأول من الكونيات و الذي كان ككل شيء في العلوم،
was Aristotelian science, and that was hierarchical.
كان علماً أرسطي (نسبةً لأرسطو) و كان هرمياً.
The earth is in the center, then there are these crystal spheres,
الأرض في الوسط، ويوجد هذه البلورات الكروية،
the sun, the moon, the planets and finally the celestial sphere,
الشمس، القمر، الكواكب، و أخيراً الكرات السماوية
where the stars are. And everything in this universe has a place.
حيث توجد النجوم، و كل شيء في هذا الكون لديه مكان.
And Aristotle’s law of motion was that everything
و كان قانون أرسطو للحركة أن كل شيء
goes to its natural place, which was of course,
يذهب لمكانه الطبيعي، ، و الذي كان طبعاً
the rule of the society that Aristotle lived in,
دور المجتمع الذي عاش به أرسطو
and more importantly, the medieval society that, through Christianity,
و الأهم من ذلك، مجتمعات القرون الوسطى من خلال المسيحية
embraced Aristotle and blessed it.
اعتنقت مذهب أرسطو و باركت به.
And the idea is that everything is defined.
وفكرة أن كل شيء هو مُعرّف.
Where something is, is defined with respect to this last sphere,
حيث أن شيء ما هو معرف من ناحية النجم الأخير،
the celestial sphere, outside of which is this eternal,
الكرات السماوية، بعيداً عن أن هذا الشيء هو أبدي
perfect realm, where lives God,
مملكة حقيقية، حيث يعيش الله،
who is the ultimate judge of everything.
و الذي هو الحكم المطلق لكل شيء.
So that is both Aristotelian cosmology,
لذا هذا هو علم الكونيات الآرسطي
and in a certain sense, medieval society.
وبمفهوم محدد، ، مجتمعات القرون الوسطى
Now, in the 17th century there was a revolution in thinking about
الآن، في القرن السابع عشر، ، كانت هناك ثورة في تفكير نيوتن
space and time and motion and so forth of Newton.
عن الفضاء و الوقت و الحركة و هلّم جراً ..
And at the same time there was a revolution in social thought
و بنفس الوقت كانت هناك ثورة في التفكير الاجتماعي
of John Locke and his collaborators.
لجون لوك و معاونوه.
And they were very closely associated.
و كانوا مترابطين بشكل قريب جداً.
In fact, Newton and Locke were friends.
في الحقيقة، نيوتن و لوكي كانا أصدقاءاً،
Their way of thinking about space and time and motion on the one hand,
طريقتهما في التفكير عن الزمان والمكان و الحركة، من ناحية
and a society on the other hand, were closely related.
و التفكير عن المجتمع من ناحية أخرى، كانا متقاربين لحد كبير.
And let me show you.
و دعوني أعرض لكم،
In a Newtonian universe, there’s no center -- thank you.
، في كون نيوتين، لا يوجد مركز، شكراً.
There are particles and they move around
يوجد جسيمات تتحرك
with respect to a fixed, absolute framework of space and time.
حول إطار ثابت و مطلق من الزمان و المكان.
It’s meaningful to say absolutely where something is in space,
من المفيد القول بأن هناك حتماً شيء ما في الفضاء
because that’s defined, not with respect to say, where other things are,
هذا يحدد ، و ليس فيما يتعلق بالحديث، حيث توجد بقية الأشياء.
but with respect to this absolute notion of space,
وبخصوص هذا التصور للفضاء،
which for Newton was God.
و الذي كان بالنسبة لنيوتن هو الله.
Now, similarly, in Locke’s society there are individuals
و الآن و على نحو مماثل، في مجتمع لوك يوجد أفراد
who have certain rights, properties in a formal sense,
لديهم حقوق محددة و خصائص في الإدراك الرسمي
and those are defined with respect to some absolute,
و هم محددون ببعض الثوابت
abstract notions of rights and justice, and so forth,
و التصورات التجريدية للحقوق و العدالة و هكذا ..
which are independent of what else has happened in the society.
و التي هي مستقلة عما يحدث في المجتمع
Of who else there is, of the history and so forth.
و ما يوجد أيضاً، التاريخ و هكذا ..
There is also an omniscient observer
هناك أيضاً المراقب العالم بكل شيء
who knows everything, who is God,
ويعلم بكل شيء، وهو الله،
who is in a certain sense outside the universe,
الذي هو بمفهوم محدد خارج هذا الكون
because he has no role in anything that happens,
سبب أن ليس له دور بأي شيء يحدث
but is in a certain sense everywhere,
و لكن بمفهوم محدد كل مكان
because space is just the way that God knows
لأن الفضاء هو فقط الطريقة التي يعلم الله بها
where everything is, according to Newton, OK?
كل شيء وفقاً لنيوتين، تماماً؟
So this is the foundations of what’s called, traditionally,
إذاً هذه هي مبادئ ما ندعوه تقليدياً
liberal political theory and Newtonian physics.
نظرية السياسة الليبرالية و الفيزياء النيوتينية،
Now, in the 20th century we had a revolution
الآن، في القرن العشرين، كان لدينا ثورة
that was initiated at the beginning of the 20th century,
بدأت في بداية القرن العشرين،
and which is still going on.
و ما زالت مستمرة حتى الآن.
It was begun with the invention
بدأت باختراع
of relativity theory and quantum theory.
نظرية النسبية ونظرية الكم.
And merging them together to make the final quantum theory
و دمجهم سوياً لتشكيل نظرية الكم الأخيرة
of space and time and gravity, is the culmination of that,
للزمان و المكان و الجاذبية، و هذا هو أوج ذلك،
something that’s going on right now.
و هو ما يتم مواصلة العمل عليه الآن.
And in this universe there’s nothing fixed and absolute. Zilch, OK.
و في هذا الكون، لا يوجد شيء ثابت و مطلق، لا شيء. تماماً.
This universe is described by being a network of relationships.
هذا الكون يوصف بكونه شبكة من العلاقات.
Space is just one aspect, so there’s no meaning to say
الفضاء هو جانب وحيد، لذا لا معنى لقول
absolutely where something is.
أين يوجد شيء ما بشكل مطلق.
There’s only where it is relative to everything else that is.
يوجد فقط في حال كونه متعلق بكل شيء آخر هو فيه.
And this network of relations is ever-evolving.
و هذه الشبكة من العلاقات تتطور تدريجياً.
So we call it a relational universe.
لذا ندعوه بالكون العلائقي.
All properties of things are about these kinds of relationships.
كل خصائص الأشياء هي عبارة عن هذه الأنواع من العلاقات
And also, if you’re embedded in such a network of relationships,
أيضاً، إذا اندمجت في مثل هذه الشبكة من العلاقات،
your view of the world has to do with what information
نظرتك للعالم ستكون بما ستصلك من معلومات
comes to you through the network of relations.
من خلال شبكة العلاقات
And there’s no place for an omniscient observer
ولا مكان للمراقب الذي يعرف كل شيء
or an outside intelligence knowing everything and making everything.
أو للذكاء الخارجي الذي يعلم كل شيء و يفعل كل شيء.
So this is general relativity, this is quantum theory.
لذا، هذه هي النظرية النسبية العامة، هذه هي نظرية الكم.
This is also, if you talk to legal scholars,
هذه أيضاً، في حال تكلمت مع العلماء القانونيين،
the foundations of new ideas in legal thought.
أساسيات الأفكار الجديدة في التفكير القانوني.
They’re thinking about the same things.
هم يفكرون بنفس الأشياء.
And not only that, they make the analogy
و ليس هذا فحسب، هم يستخدمون القياس
to relativity theory and cosmology often.
للنظرية النسبية و لعلم الكونيات غالباً.
So there’s an interesting discussion going on there.
لذا يوجد نقاش مشوق يدور هنا،
This last view of cosmology is called the relational view.
هذه النظرية الأخيرة لعلم الكونيات تدعى النظرة العلائقية.
So the main slogan here is that there’s nothing outside the universe,
لذا الشعار الأساسي هنا، لا يوجد شيء خارج الكون،
which means that there’s no place
و هذا يعني أنه لا يوجد مكان
to put an explanation for something outside.
لتقوم بتفسير شيء ما في الخارج
So in such a relational universe,
لذا في مثل هذا الكون العلائقي،
if you come upon something that’s ordered and structured,
إذا قابلت شيء ما مرتب و منتظم،
like this device here, or that device there,
مثل هذا الجهاز هنا، أو ذلك الجهاز هناك،
or something beautiful, like all the living things,
، أو شيء ما جميل ككل الكائنات الحية،
all of you guys in the room --
أو كل الفتيان في هذه الغرفة ..
"guys" in physics, by the way, is a generic term: men and women.
بالمناسبة، "الفتيان" في الفيزياء هو مصطلح عام تعني الرجال و النساء
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Then you want to know, you’re a person,
إذاً تريد أن تعلم، أنت شخص
you want to know how is it made.
و تريد أن تعلم كيف تم صنعه.
And in a relational universe the only possible explanation was, somehow it made itself.
و في الكون العلائقي، التفسير الوحيد كان بطريقة ما تم صنعه بنفسه.
There must be mechanisms of self-organization
يجب أن يكون هناك آليات من التنظيم الذاتي
inside the universe that make things.
داخل هذا الكون و الذي يصنع الأشياء
Because there’s no place to put a maker outside,
بسبب أنه لا يوجد مكان لوضع الصانع خارجاً
as there was in the Aristotelian and the Newtonian universe.
كما كان في الكون النيوتوني و الآرسطي،
So in a relational universe we must have processes of self-organization.
لذا في الكون العلائقي يجب أن يكون لدينا عمليات من التنظيم الذاتي.
Now, Darwin taught us that there are processes of self-organization
الآن، داروين علمنا بأنه هناك عمليات من التنظيم الذاتي،
that suffice to explain all of us and everything we see.
و التي تكفي لتفسيرنا و لتفسير كل شيء نراه،
So it works. But not only that,
لذا هذا يعمل، ليس هذا فحسب
if you think about how natural selection works,
إذا فكرت كيف يعمل الانتقاء الطبيعي،
then it turns out that natural selection
يثبت في النهاية أن الانتقاء الطبيعي
would only make sense in such a relational universe.
سيكون له معنى فقط في مثل هذا الكون العلائقي.
That is, natural selection works on properties,
هذا هو، الانتقاء الطبيعي يعمل وفقاً لخصائص،
like fitness, which are about relationships
مثل الملائمة، و التي هي علاقة
of some species to some other species.
من بعض الأجزاء إلى أجزاء أخرى.
Darwin wouldn’t make sense in an Aristotelian universe,
داروين لم يكن ليفهم معنى الكون الآرسطي
and wouldn’t really make sense in a Newtonian universe.
و لكم يكن ليفهم حقيقةً الكون النيوتوني.
So a theory of biology based on natural selection
إذاً نظرية علم الأحياء المبنية على الانتقاء الطبيعي
requires a relational notion of
تتطلب نظرية علائقية
what are the properties of biological systems.
لماهية خصائص الأنظمة البيولوجية.
And if you push that all the way down, really,
و إذا اسقطت كل هذه العملية، حقيقةً
it makes the best sense in a relational universe
سيتكون أفضل فهم في الكون العلائقي
where all properties are relational.
حيث كل الخصائص هي علائقية.
Now, not only that, but Einstein taught us
الآن، ليس هذا فحسب، و لكن آينشتاين علمنا
that gravity is the result of the world being relational.
بأن الجاذبية هي نتيجة كون العالم علائقي.
If it wasn’t for gravity, there wouldn’t be life,
إن لم تكن الجاذبية، لن يكون هناك حياة،
because gravity causes stars to form and live for a very long time,
لأن الجاذبية تسبب تشكل النجوم لتبقى حية لحياة طويلة جداً،
keeping pieces of the world, like the surface of the Earth,
و التي تحافظ على أجزاء من هذا العالم،-مثل سطح الأرض-
out of thermal equilibrium for billions of years so life can evolve.
بعيداً عن التوازن الحراري لمليارات السنوات لكي تتطور الحياة.
In the 20th century,
في القرن العشرين،
we saw the independent development of two big themes in science.
رأينا تطور مستقل لموضوعين كبيرين في العلم.
In the biological sciences, they explored
في العلوم البيولوجية، فسروا
the implications of the notion that order and complexity
تضمين فكرة الترتيب، و التعقيد
and structure arise in a self-organized way.
و البنية التي نهضت في طريق منتظم ذاتياً.
That was the triumph of Neo-Darwinism and so forth.
هذا كان النصر للداروينية الجديدة و هكذا ..
And slowly, that idea is leaking out to the cognitive sciences,
وببطء، بدأت تتضح الفكرة للعلوم المعرفية،
the human sciences, economics, et cetera.
العلوم الإنسانية، الاقتصاد ..الخ ..
At the same time, we physicists
في الوقت ذاته، نحن الفيزيائيون
have been busy trying to make sense of
كنا منشغلين لمحاولة فهم
and build on and integrate the discoveries
وبناء ودمج اكتشافات
of quantum theory and relativity.
نظرية الكم و النظرية النسبية.
And what we’ve been working out is the implications, really,
و ما كنا نستنبطه هو تضمين، حقيقةً،
of the idea that the universe is made up of relations.
فكرة أن الكون عبارة عن علاقات.
21st-century science is going to be driven
علم القرن الواحد والعشرين سيقاد
by the integration of these two ideas:
بتكامل هاتين الفكرتين:
the triumph of relational ways of thinking
انتصار الطريقة العلائقية للتفكير
about the world, on the one hand,
بهذا العالم، هذا من ناحية،
and self-organization or Darwinian ways of thinking about the world,
و من ناحية أخرى، التنظيم الذاتي أو الطريقة الداروينية
on the other hand.
للتفكير بهذا العالم، من ناحية أخرى.
And also, is that in the 21st century
و أيضاً في القرن الواحد والعشرين،
our thinking about space and time and cosmology,
طريقنا بالتفكير عن الزمان و المكان و علم الكونيات،
and our thinking about society are both going to continue to evolve.
طريقتنا بالتفكير عن المجتمع ستتجه للتطور تدريجياً.
And what they’re evolving towards is the union
و ما يتطورون باتجاهه هو اتحاد
of these two big ideas, Darwinism and relationalism.
هاتين الفكرتين الكبيرتين: الداروينية و العلائقية.
Now, if you think about democracy from this perspective,
الآن إذا فكرت بالديمقراطية من هذا المنظور،
a new pluralistic notion of democracy would be one that recognizes
نظرية تعددية جديدة من الديمقراطية ستكون واحدة تعترف
that there are many different interests, many different agendas,
بأنه يوجد اهتمامات كثيرة مختلفة، برامج كثيرة مختلفة،
many different individuals, many different points of view.
أفراد كُثر مختلفون، وجهات نظر كثيرة مختلفة.
Each one is incomplete, because you’re embedded
كل منها غير مكتمل، لأنك مندمج
in a network of relationships.
بشبكة من العلاقات.
Any actor in a democracy is embedded
أي ممثل في الديمقراطية هو مندمج
And you understand some things better than other things,
و أنت تفهم بعض الأشياء أكثر من فهمك لأشياء أخرى،
and because of that there’s a continual jostling
و بسبب ذلك، يوجد اصطدام متواصل،
and give and take, which is politics.
و أخذ وعطاء، و التي هي السياسة.
And politics is, in the ideal sense,
و السياسة في التفكير المثالي،
the way in which we continually address
هي الطريقة التي نوجه كلامنا بشكل مستمر
our network of relations in order to achieve
لشبكة من العلاقات لتحقيق
a better life and a better society.
حياة أفضل و مجتمع أفضل
And I also think that science will never go away and --
و أعتقد أيضاً بأن العلم لن يزول أبداً-
I’m finishing on this line.
أنا انتهيت عند هذا .
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
In fact, I’m finished. Science will never go away.
في الواقع لقد انتهيت، العلم لن يزول أبداً.